Guide to the Thomas Nelson Page Papers, 1739-1927 and undated, bulk 1885-1920
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Thomas Nelson Page papers 1739-1927 and undated, bulk 1885-1920
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Page, Thomas Nelson
12.4 linear feet Extent: 9329 Items
Virginia lawyer and writer; ambassador to Italy from 1913-1919. The Thomas Nelson Page Papers span the years 1739-1927. Personal and professional correspondence, legal and business papers, writings, diplomatic dispatches, clippings and other items (chiefly 1885-1920) relate to Page's legal and literary career; his activities as a lyceum lecturer; his marriages and family relations; and his interest in civic affairs, plantation life, social reform and race relations in the United States, particularly during and after Reconstruction; American politics and diplomacy, especially during World War I; and European travel. Many of his papers directly relate to his term as ambassador to Italy during World War I, from 1913 to 1919.
RL.00988
Language: Material in English and Italian
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Thomas Nelson Page Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1937.
Biographical Note
1853 Apr. 23 Page born on Oakland Plantation, Hanover County, Va.
1869-1872 Attended Washington College
1874 Graduated from University of Virginia Law School
1884 Published "Marse Chan"
1886 July 28 Married Anne Seddon Bruce
1887 Published "Unc' Edingburgh's Drowndin'" and "No Haid Pawn"
1888 Dec. 22 Death of Anne Seddon Bruce Page
1889-1893 Toured on lyceum circuit
1893 Married Florence Field
1895 Headed alumni campaign to raise funds for rebuilding of University of Virginia rotunda
1899 Oakland Plantation burned
1913 Chairman of Reception Committe for Wilson's Inauguration
1913 July 6 Appointed ambassador to Italy
1916 Returned home on leave
1916 July Resumed post in Italy
1919 July 5 Resigned post of ambassador
1919 Wrote volume on Italy and the World War
1921 May Florence Page died
1922 Nov. 1 Died at Oakland Plantation
Collection Overview
The Thomas Nelson Page Papers span the years 1739-1927, with the majority of the materials dating from the 1880s to 1920. The papers include personal and professional correspondence, legal and business papers, writings, diplomatic dispatches, clippings and other items, all relating to Page's legal and literary career. Topics include his activities as a lyceum lecturer; his marriages and family relations; his role in and perspective on American politics and foreign relations, particularly during World War II; travels in Europe; and his interest in civic affairs, social reform and race relationsin the United States, particularly during and following Reconstruction. Collection is arranged in the following series: Correspondence, Legal and Financial Papers, Writings and Speeches, Diplomacy, Visual Materials, Personal Papers, and Clippings Two oversize newspapers are described in a series at the end of the finding aid.
In the Correspondence Series, the largest in the collection, letters prior to 1880 include personal correspondence from various members of the Page family, especially between Thomas Nelson Page, his mother, Elizabeth Burwell (Nelson) Page, and brother, Rosewell Page, who lived at the ancestral estate, "Oakland," in Hanover County, Virginia. Page describes his political activities in letters concerning the presidential campaigns of 1912 and 1916. Correspondence from this period also includes personal letters to members of the family describing new experiences in diplomatic life, and routine business correspondence. Significant correspondents in the series include C. F. Adams, Grover Cleveland, Josephus Daniels, J. C. Harris, William D. Howells, Robert Lansing, Robert T. Lincoln, Henry C. Lodge, Theodore Roosevelt, E. Root, J. M. Stoddart, and William H. Taft. For some of these individuals only one or two pieces of correspondence exist. Another set of correspondence, dated 1883-1912 and interfiled at the end of the correspondence series, comprises photocopies of letters (and a few other items, including a telegram, Christmas greeting, and obituary clipping on Henry Hobson) chiefly from Page to close friend Henry Wise Hobson (1858-1898), originally of Virginia, and to his wife Katherine. Notes: Originals for photocopies are in the donor's possession. The collection also includes two scrapbooks, found in the Personal Papers Series, containing cards and envelopes from distinguished persons. This series also houses documents related to Page's ties with the University of Virginia, personal reminiscences, various fragmentary notes, and a journal from 1863. Four folders of carbon copies of diplomatic dispatches from Page to the U.S. State Department and to President Woodrow Wilson, along with other papers related to his diplomatic activities, can be found in the Diplomacy Series. Another small group, the Legal and Financial Series, houses documents relating to Page's properties and other business affairs. The Writings and Speeches Series contains many manuscripts and drafts of political and literary speeches, memoirs, essays, and articles, but none of Page's major literary works. Several folders of materials in this series contain Page's detailed journalistic notes describing his trips in 1916 to the war fronts in Italy and France. Extensive folders of cuttings in the Clippings Series were taken from both American and Italian newspapers, and comprise a significant portion of the collection. The clippings refer to events in Page's career such as lyceum appearances, political appointments, and political speeches, both in the United States and in Italy. In addition, Page clipped articles referring to race relations in the United States, particularly in the South. The clippings also document national and global events during Page's years as an ambassador to Italy from 1913 to 1919, and provide rich background material for a study of United States foreign relations with Italy and other countries during World War I. There are also a few photographs in the Visual Materials Series, some of which depict scenes from wartime Italy.
Subject Headings
Page, Thomas Nelson, 1853-1922; Page, Elizabeth Burwell Nelson; Hobson, Henry Wise, 1858-1898; Page family; Page, Rosewell, 1858-1939; Authors, American -- Virginia; Ambassadors -- United States; Lyceums -- United States; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924; Presidents -- United States -- Election -- 1912; Presidents -- United States -- Election -- 1916; African Americans -- Southern States -- 1865-1951; Reconstruction -- Southern States; France -- Description and travel; Italy -- Description and travel; Italy -- History -- 1914-1922; Italy -- Foreign relations -- United States; United States -- Foreign Service -- History; World War, 1914-1918 -- Italy; World War, 1914-1918 -- United States; Southern States -- Race relations -- History -- 1865-1951; United States -- Foreign relations -- Italy; Clippings; Photographs; Scrapbooks
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence Series, 1739-1927 and undated, (13 boxes)
  Arranged in chronological order.
  - 1739-1817 (Box 1)
  - 1836-1839 (Box 1)
  - 1850-1896 (Box 1)
  - 1897-1899 (Box 2)
  - 1900 Jan.-1902 June (Box 3)
  - 1902 July-1904 Aug. (Box 4)
  - 1904 Sept.-1908 Dec. (Box 5)
  - 1909 Jan.-1911 Jan. (Box 6)
  - 1911 Feb.-1913 Mar. (Box 7)
  - 1913 Mar.-1913 Aug. (Box 8)
  - 1913 Sept.-1916 Sept. (Box 9)
  - 1916 Oct.-1918 June (Box 10)
  - 1918 July-1919 Dec. (Box 11)
  - 1920-1927 and undated (Box 12)
  - Undated correspondence, (4 folders) (Box 13)
  - 1883-1912 and undated: Correspondence from Page to Henry Hobson and his sister, Katherine (Kitty) Hobson, (2 folders) (Box 13)
- Legal and Financial Papers Series, 1875-1923, (1 box)
  Consists of records dealing with royalties due to Thomas Nelson Page and property owned by Page. Arranged in alphabetical order.
  - Bills and accounts, 1879-1920, (2 folders) (Box 13)
  - Checks and receipts, 1882-1913 (Box 13)
  - Construction of residence in Washington, D.C., 1893-1897 (Box 13)
  - Hanover printing and publishing company, 1918, 1923 (Box 13)
  - Income accounts, 1903, 1915-1919 (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous, 1912-1913 (Box 13)
  - Mont Air farm, 1901-1913 (Box 13)
  - Real estate, 1898-1916 (Box 13)
  - Royalty reports, 1899-1919 (Box 13)
  - Various legal papers, 1875-1919 (Box 13)
- Writings and Speeches Series, 1863-1920 and undated, (2 boxes)
  Consists primarily of literary manuscripts, addresses and speeches written by Thomas Nelson Page. Also included are various other writers on Southern history. Arranged in chronological order.
  - 1863-1864, Extract from H. Nelson Gay's articles including reference to Pius IX's offer of intervention in American civil war, Oct 18, 1863 (Box 14)
  - 1876, Page, Thomas Nelson, Copies of material on reconstruction in South Carolina (Box 14)
  - 1890, Page, Rosewell, When I was a Little Boy, rpt. 1970 (Box 14)
  - 1893 Apr., Richmond, Virginia, Wise, B.H., Thomas Nelson Page (Box 14)
  - 1897, Washington D.C., Page, Thomas Nelson, Colonel William Nelson of Oakland (Box 14)
  - 1898 July 4, Rio de Janerio, Brazil, editorials from the press of Rio de Janerio (Box 14)
  - 1898 Oct. 19, Hobson, Henry W., Memorial and resolutions on death of... (Box 14)
  - Circa 1898-1903, Book review lists (Box 14)
  - 1899 Mar. 29, Wilson, Robert Burns, The Song of the Lark (Box 14)
  - 1901, Page, Thomas Nelson, On the Nile, reprint, 1970 (Box 14)
  - 1901 Jan., Page, Thomas Nelson, On the Nile, typescript, journal of a tour in Egypt, (2 folders) (Box 14)
  - Circa 1901, Washington D.C., Page, Thomas Nelson, remarks as toastmaster at Jefferson dinner (Box 14)
  - 1906, Page, Thomas Nelson, Mediterranean Winter, Journal and Letters, reprint 1971 (Box 14)
  - 1907, See UVA annual Corks and Curls, Page, Thomas Nelson, Recollections of the University of Virginia (Box 14)
  - 1908,Washington D.C., Page, Thomas Nelson, In Memoriam: Thomas Seddon Bruce (Box 14)
  - 1909 Apr. 28, Washington D.C., Ceremony in honor of L'Enfant (Box 14)
  - 1911 Jan. 27, Memorandum Relative to the Work of the American Forestry Association for 1911 (Box 14)
  - 1912, Page, Thomas Nelson, North African Journal, reprint 1970 (Box 14)
  - 1912 Nov. 27, Page, Thomas Nelson, Mr. Wilson's Nomination to the Governorship of New Jersey (Box 14)
  - 1912 Dec. 3, Mr. Kirkwood and Mr. MacVeagh and Mr. Windom, Mr. Cameron, In Regard to Civil Service (Box 14)
  - 1912 Dec. 10, Page, Thomas Nelson, Personal Recollections of the Opening of the Civil War (Box 14)
  - 1912 Dec. 12, The Baltimore Convention of 1912 (Box 14)
  - Circa 1912, Richmond, Virginia, unidentified address, attributed to Page, fragment, typed, pp. 35-83 (Box 14)
  - 1913 Jan. 4, Washington D.C., Weller, Charles Frederick, American Needs and Opportunities (Box 14)
  - 1913 Feb. 22, Washington D.C., Page, Thomas Nelson, Henry Clay and the Treaty of Ghent (Box 14)
  - 1914, Page, Thomas Nelson, Has Civilization Failed? (Box 14)
  - 1914 Feb., Rome, Italy, Page, Thomas Nelson, Lines of the Room in which Keats Died (Box 14)
  - 1915, Page, Thomas Nelson, What America Stands for... (Box 14)
  - 1915 Nov. 22, Rome, Italy, Pope Address to the members of the Society for the Preservation of the Faith in Rome (Box 14)
  - 1916, Page, Thomas Nelson, President Wilson's Critics- A Challenge Not a Defense (Box 14)
  - 1916, Page, Thomas Nelson, The United States (Box 14)
  - 1916 July, Chantilly, France, Page, Thomas Nelson, A casual glimpse of the French front in Champagne (Box 14)
  - 1916 Sept. 13-18, Udine, Italy, Page, Thomas Nelson, journal of a visit to the Italian front, ( 2 copies) (Box 14)
  - 1917 Feb. 22, Rome, Italy, Page, Thomas Nelson, Address... delivered Feb. 22nd 1917 at the American Embassy (Box 14)
  - 1917 July 4, Rome, Italy, Page, Thomas Nelson, Speech...Delivered at the Campidoglio,... to Celebrate America's Entrance into the War (Box 14)
  - 1917 Oct. 1, Rome, Italy, Page, Thomas Nelson, Speech delivered at luncheon given by Italian American Union to Col. Baker's Red Cross Commission (Box 14)
  - 1918 Jan. 15, Rome, Italy, Page, Thomas Nelson, speech delivered at Campidoglio (Box 15)
  - 1918 Apr. 2, Rome, Italy, Page, Thomas Nelson, Speech in honor of Secretary of War Baker (Box 15)
  - 1918 Apr. 7, Rome, Italy. Speech delivered at Campidoglio by Page (Box 15)
  - 1918 Apr. 9, Corriere d'Italia, Thomas Nelson Page (Box 15)
  - 1918 July, Rome, Italy, Page, Thomas Nelson, To My Compatriots, the American Soldiers in Italy (Box 15)
  - 1918 Aug. 1, Rome, Italy, Page, Thomas Nelson, Welcome addressed by U.S. Ambassador to Officers and Men of 32nd U.S. Infantry Regiment (Box 15)
  - 1918 Oct. 13, Rome, Italy, Page, Thomas Nelson, Address in an assembly before the embassy (Box 15)
  - 1918, Page, Thomas Nelson, Economic Conditions in the Southern Confederacy (Box 15)
  - 1919 Mar. 21, Rome, Italy, Page, Thomas Nelson, Greetings to the soldiers of U.S.A. Coming to Italy on Leave (Box 15)
  - 1919 Mar. 27, Page, Thomas Nelson, Introduction to Reminiscences Revd. Wm M Dame (Box 15)
  - 1919 June, Rome, Italy, Page, Thomas Nelson, speech introducing Miss Winifred Hold (Box 15)
  - 1919 Aug. 15, Richmond, Va., Page, Thomas Nelson, Address delivered in Hall of Virginia House of Delegates in Celebration of the 300th Anniversary of the Assembling of the 1st General Assembly of Virginia at Jamestown (Box 15)
  - 1919 Sept. 5, Page, Thomas Nelson, address to the New England Manufacturers Association (Box 15)
  - 1919, Page, Thomas Nelson, A few reflections in the interest of fair play (Box 15)
  - 1919 Sept., York Harbor, Maine, Page, Thomas Nelson, On the ratification of the peace treaty (Box 15)
  - Circa 1920, Page, Thomas Nelson, Promotion of international peace and especially promotion of cordial relations between the two branches of the english speaking race (Box 15)
  - Undated Writings
    - Page, Thomas Nelson, printed poem and Personal Recollections of Thomas Nelson Page, by S.A. Steel (Box 15)
    - Page, Thomas Nelson, The Ballad of Willy's Horn (Box 15)
    - Page, Thomas Nelson, Poe: The First American Man of Letters (Box 15)
    - Page, Thomas Nelson, fragment from Unc' Edinburgh's Drowndin' (Box 15)
    - Page, Thomas Nelson, Memorandum and specifications of a stone and timber dam to be built at Fulcher's Mill on Little River, Hanover Co., Va. (Box 15)
    - Page, Thomas Nelson, Introduction to Gordon Keith (Box 15)
    - Page, Thomas Nelson, Mogul's Last Race (Box 15)
    - Page, Thomas Nelson, Introduction to Mr. Leavitt's Book (Box 15)
    - Page, Thomas Nelson, Sonnets (Box 15)
    - Page, Rosewell, Introduction to The Commentaries of an American Ambassador during the World War (Box 15)
    - Page, Thomas Nelson, My Opinion of Reviews of My Books (Box 15)
    - Page, Thomas Nelson, Prospects of the International Association of Newspapers and Authors (Box 15)
    - Weller, Charles Frederick, Rural Recreation (Box 15)
    - King, Henry C., Some Notes on the Negro (Box 15)
    - Page, Thomas Nelson, Thomas Jefferson: Apostle of Liberty (Box 15)
    - The Major's Story (Box 15)
    - Hampden-Sidney College (Box 15)
    - Page, Thomas Nelson, Polly, dramatization fragment (Box 15)
    - de Leon, Perry M., The Confederate States Navy in the Civil War (Box 15)
    - Carey, William, fragment of memoir (Box 15)
    - Page, Thomas Nelson, literary fragments (Box 15)
- Diplomacy Series, 1915-1919 and undated, (2 boxes)
  Various official missives and documents arising from Page's activities diplomatic activies in Europe. Arranged in chronological order.
  - 1915-1919, Duplicate carbons, (4 folders) (Box 15)
  - 1915-1919 and undated, Miscellaneous papers, (3 folders) (Box 16)
  - Passports and related documents (Box 16)
- Visual Materials Series, circa 1915-undated, (1 box)
  Photographs include family trips, the campus of the University of Virginia, and the effects of World War I on Italy.
  - Blueprints and maps (Box 16)
  - Photographs (Box 16)
  - Story illustrations (Box 16)
- Personal Papers Series, 1863-1917 and undated, (2 boxes)
  Of note are the materials on the inauguration of Woodrow Wilson. Another section is dedicated to the rebuilding efforts at the University of Virginia. Arranged in alphabetical order.
  - Bylaws and house rules: York Harbor Reading Room, 1901 (Box 16)
  - Cards and invitations (Box 16)
  - Inauguration of Woodrow Wilson, 1913 (Box 16)
  - Journal, 1863 (Box 16)
  - Miscellaneous printed material; circulars, etc., (3 folders) (Box 17)
  - Recollections and Reflections, Thomas Nelson Page (Box 17)
  - University of Virginia, (2 folders) (Box 17)
  - Various forms, lists, invitations and miscellaneous papers (Box 17)
  - Various fragmentary notes and lists, 1865-1917 and undated (Box 17)
  - Various notes, lists and other papers (Box 17)
- Clippings Series, 1882-1919, (8 boxes)
  Extensive collection of clippings taken from major American and Italian newspapers, chiefly from the period when Page was writing about race relations and other social issues in the United States, and during his politically active period from 1910 to the 1920s. Most of the American clippings have been photocopied from the originals. Other clippings may be fragile; handle with care. Photocopies may be necessary to access material. Arranged within geographical categories chronologically by date.
  - American, 1882-1902 (Box 17)
  - American, 1903-1926 and undated (Box 18)
  - French, 1904, 1915-1919 (Box 18)
  - German, 1897 (Box 18)
  - Italian, 1915 Apr.-1917 May (Box 19)
  - Italian, 1917 May-1917 July (Box 20)
  - Italian, 1917 Aug.-1917 Oct. (Box 21)
  - Italian, 1917 Nov.-1919 Jan. (Box 22)
  - Italian, 1919 Jan.-1919 Apr. (Box 23)
  - Italian, 1919 Apr.-1921 (Box 24)
- Oversize Material, 1898-1912, (1 folder)
  - Clippings Series, 1898-1912
    - The Sun (N.Y.C.), 1898 Aug. 8 (article marked: "Seizure of the Ladrone Islands") (Opaperfolder 1)
      [Extremely fragile. Consult with a Reference Archivist to use this item.]
    - New York Herald, 1912 Dec. 5 (Christmas edition): Christmases of the Nation, by Thomas Nelson Page (Opaperfolder 1)